{
  "name": "Prehistory Period (Before 4th Centuries CE)",
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "The History of Assam can be divided into_____ eras.",
      "options": [
        "A. 3 eras",
        "B. 4 eras",
        "C. 5 eras",
        "D. 6 eras"
      ],
      "answer": "B. 4 eras."
    },
    {
      "question": "In Ancient times, Assam was known by the name of",
      "options": [
        "A. Kaliabor",
        "B. Guwahati",
        "C. Pragjyotisha",
        "D. Charaideo"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Pragjyotisha"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following epics is considered as the highest source of the Prehistory period of Assam?",
      "options": [
        "A. Mahabharata",
        "B. Harshacharita",
        "C. Kalika Puran",
        "D. Arthasastra"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Kalika Puran"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the earliest king of Pragjyotishpur?",
      "options": [
        "A. Bhasakar Varman",
        "B. Mahiranga Danava",
        "C. Narakasura",
        "D. Banasura"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Mahiranga Danava"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahiranga was Sanskritized from",
      "options": [
        "A. Nilachal",
        "B. Chitrachal",
        "C. Patkai",
        "D. Mairong"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Mairong"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the ancient name of Assam mentioned in Ramayana and Mahabharata?",
      "options": [
        "A. Kamarupa",
        "B. Indraprastha",
        "C. Pragjyotishpura",
        "D. Assam"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Pragjyotishpura"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramayana, Amurtyaraja was the founder of the kingdom of?",
      "options": [
        "A. Pragjyotisha",
        "B. Kamarupa",
        "C. Harupeswar",
        "D. Cooch Behar"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Pragjyotisha"
    },
    {
      "question": "Narakasura founded which dynasty?",
      "options": [
        "A. Pala dynasty",
        "B. Varman dynasty",
        "C. Salasthamba dynasty",
        "D. Bhauma dynasty"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Bhauma dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ghatakasura was killed by?",
      "options": [
        "A. Narakasura",
        "B. Bana Raja",
        "C. Mahiranga Danava",
        "D. Bhasakar Varman"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Narakasura"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Pre-History sources, the mother of Narakasura was",
      "options": [
        "A. Dharitri",
        "B. Hidimba",
        "C. Usha",
        "D. Ulupi"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Dharitri"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ghatakasura was a ruler of the",
      "options": [
        "A. Aryans",
        "B. Kirats",
        "C. Dravidians",
        "D. Mongolians"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Kirats"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was killed by the first Naraka King Narakasura and established the Bhauma dynasty?",
      "options": [
        "A. Pushyavarman",
        "B. Ghatakasura",
        "C. Bhaskarvarman",
        "D. Gopala"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Ghatakasura"
    },
    {
      "question": "Name the two medieval texts that were compiled in the region of Assam:",
      "options": [
        "A. Ved and Puran",
        "B. Kalika Purana and Yogini Tantra",
        "C. Kaunji Khel and Yogini Tantra",
        "D. Namanjali and Kirtan"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Kalika Purana and Yogini Tantra"
    },
    {
      "question": "The tantric text 'Yogini Tantra' is dedicated to the worship of two goddesses. One is kali and the other one is?",
      "options": [
        "A. Mahamaya",
        "B. Kamakhya",
        "C. Tara Devi",
        "D. None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Kamakhya"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to which of the following 'Purana', the temple of Kamakhya was in the centre of Kamarupa?",
      "options": [
        "A. Vishnu Purana",
        "B. Kalika Purana",
        "C. Shiva Purana",
        "D. Yogini Tantra"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Kalika Purana"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the Kalika Purana, Naraka the mythological ancestor of the Varman dynasty was the son of:",
      "options": [
        "A. Varaha form of Vishnu and Bhumi",
        "B. Kartick form of Shiv and Parborti",
        "C. Srikrishna",
        "D. None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Varaha form of Vishnu and Bhumi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ranapith, Kampith, Swanapith and Saumarpith were the four divisions of the ancient Kamrupa. Which of the following historical composition mentions about these four divisions?",
      "options": [
        "A. Yogini Tantra",
        "B. Kalika Purana",
        "C. Vishnu Purana",
        "D. Mahabharat"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Yogini Tantra"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hinduism was established in Pragjyotishpura by the king",
      "options": [
        "A. Narakasur",
        "B. Sri Krishna",
        "C. Bhagadatta",
        "D. Banasur"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Narakasur"
    },
    {
      "question": "Narakasura was killed by",
      "options": [
        "A. Shiva",
        "B. Sri Krishna",
        "C. Bhagadatta",
        "D. Banasur"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Sri Krishna"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who killed Mura, the general of Narakasura?",
      "options": [
        "A. Shiva",
        "B. Sri Krishna",
        "C. Bhagadatta",
        "D. Banasur"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Sri Krishna"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the epic Mahabharata, who ruled the Pragjyotishpura kingdom during the Kurukshetra war?",
      "options": [
        "A. Bhaskarvarman",
        "B. Bhutivarman",
        "C. Narakasur",
        "D. Bhagadatta"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Bhagadutta"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which Kamrupa King took part in the Battle of Kurukshetra (the Mahabharata War)",
      "options": [
        "A. Naraka",
        "B. Bhagadatta",
        "C. Bhaskarvarman",
        "D. Vajradatta"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Bhagadatta"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Battle of Kurukshetra, Bhagadatta fought on the side of",
      "options": [
        "A. Kauravas",
        "B. Pandavas",
        "C. Arjun",
        "D. None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Kauravas"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the name of the elephant of Bhagadatta?",
      "options": [
        "A. Oiravat",
        "B. Chetak",
        "C. Langie",
        "D. Ramu"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Oiravat"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name of the Parva of Mahabharata which mentions the valor of Bhagadatta?",
      "options": [
        "A. Adi Parva (The Book of the Beginning)",
        "B. Bhishma Parva (The Book of Bhishma)",
        "C. Drona Parva (The Book of Drona)",
        "D. Karna Parva (The Book of Karna)"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Karna Parva (The Book of Karna)"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bhanumathi, The daughter of Bhagadatta was married to",
      "options": [
        "A. Arjuna",
        "B. Karna",
        "C. Duryodhana",
        "D. Dushasan"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Duryodhana"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Dighali Pukhuri in Guwahati is associated with",
      "options": [
        "A. Harjaravarman",
        "B. Narakasura",
        "C. Bhagadatta",
        "D. Bhaskarvarman"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Bhagadatta"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Kurukshetra war, Bhagadatta was slain by",
      "options": [
        "A. Nakul",
        "B. Sri Krishna",
        "C. Arjuna",
        "D. Bheema"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Arjuna"
    },
    {
      "question": "In ancient times who was the king of Vidarbha?",
      "options": [
        "A. Bhishmaka",
        "B. Narakasur",
        "C. Bhagadatta",
        "D. Marichi"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Bhishmaka"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rukmini was the princess of",
      "options": [
        "A. Kundil Nagar",
        "B. Kamrup",
        "C. Tezpur",
        "D. Sadiya"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Kundil Nagar, Sadiya"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rukmini was the daughter of",
      "options": [
        "A. Marichi",
        "B. Narakasur",
        "C. Bhagadatta",
        "D. Bhishmaka"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Bhishmaka"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who built Kundil Nagar on the bank of Kundil River?",
      "options": [
        "A. Banasur",
        "B. Bhishmaka",
        "C. Narakasur",
        "D. Bhagadatta"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Bhishmaka"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ancient city 'Bengmara' is presently known as",
      "options": [
        "A. Diphu",
        "B. Sodiya",
        "C. Tinsukia",
        "D. Dibrugarh"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Tinsukia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following was the chief weapon of war in ancient Assam?",
      "options": [
        "A. Asik",
        "B. Parsu",
        "C. Jada and Khatvanga",
        "D. All of these"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Parsu"
    },
    {
      "question": "The character Chand Sadagar is found in the tale of",
      "options": [
        "A. Aymati",
        "B. Usha",
        "C. Behula",
        "D. Sabitri"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Behula"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following place was famous for astrology?",
      "options": [
        "A. Pragjyotishpura",
        "B. Kamarupa",
        "C. Charaidew",
        "D. Saumara"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Pragjyotishpura"
    },
    {
      "question": "Assam was formerly known by the name of",
      "options": [
        "A. Vanga",
        "B. Kamarupa",
        "C. Anga",
        "D. Vaishali"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Kamarupa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which city is called 'The City of Eastern Astrology'?",
      "options": [
        "A. Pragjyotishpur",
        "B. Harupeswar",
        "C. Sri Duriya",
        "D. Tezpur"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Pragjyotishpur"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the following books is the most important literary source for the study of early history of Assam. Which is the book?",
      "options": [
        "A. The Mahabharata",
        "B. The Harshacharita",
        "C. The Kalika Purana",
        "D. The Arthashastra"
      ],
      "answer": "C. The Kalika Purana"
    },
    {
      "question": "The earliest king of Assam was-",
      "options": [
        "A. Mahiranga Danava",
        "B. Narakasura",
        "C. Bhaskaravarman",
        "D. Naranarayana"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Mahiranga Danava"
    },
    {
      "question": "The earliest historical dynasty of Assam was that of the",
      "options": [
        "A. Palas",
        "B. Varmans",
        "C. Narakas",
        "D. Salastambhas"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Varmans"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Buranjis are",
      "options": [
        "A. Autobiographical writings of the Ahom rulers",
        "B. Diaries written by the monarchs",
        "C. Chronicles",
        "D. None of the above"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Chronicles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the only Kamarupa dynasty's inscription that distinguishes between the b (ব) and v (ৱ) letters?",
      "options": [
        "A. Nidhanpur copperplate inscription",
        "B. Dubi Rock Inscription",
        "C. Nagajari-Khanikargaon rock inscription",
        "D. None of these"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Nagajari-Khanikar Gaon rock inscription"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nagajari-Khanikargaon rock inscription belongs to:",
      "options": [
        "A. Varman Dynasty",
        "B. Mlechchha dynasty",
        "C. Pala dynasty",
        "D. None of these"
      ],
      "answer": "A. Varman Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is the earliest epigraphic source discovered in Assam?",
      "options": [
        "A. Dubi Copper plate",
        "B. Parbatiya Copper plate",
        "C. Nidhanpur Copper plate",
        "D. The Umachal rock inscription"
      ],
      "answer": "D. The Umachal rock inscription"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is NOT related with the Varman king Bhaskaravarman?",
      "options": [
        "A. Dubi Copper plate",
        "B. Parbatiya Copper plate",
        "C. Nidhanpur Copper plate",
        "D. Nalanda Clay seals"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Parbatiya Copper plate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one is correct about the Umachal rock inscription?",
      "options": [
        "A. It is the earliest epigraphic source discovered in Assam",
        "B. The script of this inscription is in the eastern variety of the Gupta script and the language is Sanskrit prose",
        "C. Only A",
        "D. Both A & B"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Both A & B"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hiuen Tsang visited Assam during the reign of",
      "options": [
        "A. Naranarayan",
        "B. Brahmapala",
        "C. Balavarman",
        "D. Bhaskarvarman"
      ],
      "answer": "D. Bhaskaravarman"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hiuen Tsang described which Kamrupa king as the 'Aristocratic king of eastern India'?",
      "options": [
        "A. Brahmapala",
        "B. Balavarman",
        "C. Bhaskarvarman",
        "D. Naranarayan"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Bhaskaravarman"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the name of the book that compares Bhaskaravarman with grandfather Bhishma?",
      "options": [
        "A. Mahabharata",
        "B. Harshacharita",
        "C. Kalika Puran",
        "D. Arthasastra"
      ],
      "answer": "B. Harshacharita"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the famous teacher of Nalanda, on whose request and advice, Chinese Pilgrim Hiuen Tsang visited Kamarupa",
      "options": [
        "A. Kautilya",
        "B. Charaka",
        "C. Silabhadra",
        "D. None of these"
      ],
      "answer": "C. Silabhadra"
    },
    {
      "question": "Huen Tsang visited Assam in the year?",
      "options": [
        "A. 640 AD, In the reign of Bhaskaravarman",
        "B. 600 AD, In the reign of Pushyavarman",
        "C. 626 AD, In the reign of Bhutivarman",
        "D. 540 AD, In the reign of Bhaskaravarman"
      ],
      "answer": "A. 640 AD, In the reign of Bhaskaravarman"
    }
  ]
}
